Guide to the French Revolutionary Wars Letters and Documents
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
French revolutionary wars letters and documents
1792-1796
OSB MSS 25
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.25
(1 box)
Letters and documents regarding the activity, payment, and coordination of troops involved in the French revolutionary wars. Some letters also concern the desertion of French troops to the British side. Includes letters from Charles Bailly de Fresnay and William Cavendish Bentinck.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of materials pertaining to the French Revolutionary Wars.
France -- History -- Revolution, 1789-1799 -- Desertions; France -- History -- Revolution, 1789-1799; Bailly de Fresnay, Charles Gaspard Elisabeth Joseph, Marquis de, 1765-1850; Bentinck, William Henry Cavendish, Lord, 1774-1839
- Letters and Documents
  - Bailly de Fresnay, Charles Gaspart, Elisabeth Joseph, Marquis de, 1765-1850
    - ALS (in French) to [Sir David Dundas?], Wildsgemsen, 1795 Mar 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Reports on his activities including an unfortunate incident in which a fight broke out between a detachment of his troops and some peasants.
    - ALS in (French) to unnamed recipient, Otterburg, 1795 Apr 4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Informs the recipient that he has been put in charge of transporting rations and supplies from Otterburg to Bremen.
    - ALS (in French) to unnamed recipient, [n.p.], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Concerns problems with his troops.
  - Bentinck, Lord William Cavendish, 1774-1839
    - ALS (in French) to Sir George Don, Nienburg, 1796 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Concerns the embarrassing problem of being able to pay officers only half what they are due. Asks Don to send him some money on account.
    - Letter (copy, in French) to Captain Nacquart, Nienburg, 1795 Nov 19 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Concerns problems of coordination in strategy between the British High Command and her Dutch allies.
    - ALS (in French) to unnamed recipient, Bremen, 1796 Jan 9 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Sends the names of 13 French officers who want to join the British Army.
  - Béthisy de Mézières, Richard Henri Charles de, 1770-1827. ALS (in French) to unnamed recipient, Salzburg, 1795 Mar 16 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    From the commander of an advances outpost to his superior pleading for the relief of his squadron.
  - Brownrigg, Sir Robert, 1759-1833. ALS to Sir George Don, [n.p.], [n.y.] Mar 21 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Choiseul Stainville, Antoine Clériadus Gabriel, Duc de, 1760-1838. LS (in secretary's hand, in French) to Frederick Augustus, Duke of York, Driel, 1794 Sep 4 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Asks permission to raise a fourth squadron of his regiment. The cost would be 30 louis per man fully equipped and mounted.
  - De la Porte, Mr. ALS (in French) to Sir David Dundas, Bremen, 1795 Jun 2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Asks that General Dundas will see fit to arrange passages to England for those French gentlemen who wish to serve under British Command.
  - Dundas, Sir David, 1735-1820. ALS to Sir George Don, Lingen, [ca. 1795] Feb 28 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Concerns communication and logistic problems for the English army operating against the French in the Netherlands.
  - Durell, Thomas. "List of captive French prisoners to be exchanged" (holograph, signed), Hoxter, 1795 Aug 26 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Includes their rank, date of capture, and regiment.
  - Harcourt, William Harcourt, 3d Earl, 1743-1830. ALS (in French) to Mr. Duhon, Bremen, 1792 Apr 2 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Warns Duhon that he is responsible for detachment having requisitioned food from civilians.
  - Kielmansegge, Comte de. Letter (copy, in French) to Lord William Bentinck, Hanover, 1795, Dec 23 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Reports "les etats allemands de La Majestie" do not want expatriate Dutch soldiers on their territory.
  - Menu, H., abbé. ALS (in French) to unnamed recipient, Minden, 1795 Mar 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Concerns a messenger sent to Menu from the recipient, a colonel.
  - Mozane, Cananas du. 2 ALS (in French) to Sir James Henry Craig, [v.p.], 1794 Jul 17, Nov 8 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    The first letter suggests the extension of an amnesty to those French soldiers willing to desert the British. The second reports on the progress of their programs and includes descriptions of specific cases of desertions.
- Manuscripts, n.d.
  - "Etat du depot á Etablir, le plus prés possible Des frontiers," anonymous manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Extrait d'une lettre de London du 2 Oct 1796," anonymous manuscript, 1796 Oct 2 (Box 1, Folder 18)